[music]
>> Welcome to 2026 release wave one of
Business Central launch edition. This
video is about all the things we did for
financial reporting.
So why did we invest in this? Well, if
we allow
controllers and the finance department
to have to work better with financial
reporting, we are actually helping every
single customer Business Central. Every
single customer Business Central use the
finance module and a lot of them use
financial reporting. So it's better
overviews, faster setups, smart smarter
workflows of of using financial
reporting and just boosted productivity,
also something we call quality of life.
So let's dive into it.
The highlights of financial reporting
falls into three types of personas.
Okay, first of all, a new tile view for
everyone, but then categories, life
cycle status and company specific
defaults are for the financial reporting
authors.
The next two, dimension perspective and
scheduling, are for the financial
reporting consumers or users that
actually use the report, run the report.
And finally, for the administrators or
the controllers, internal control, we
have a new audit log where you can see
who actually use the system, who use the
financial reporting
and for what.
Okay, so for everyone, we have added
[clears throat] a new tile view to to
the
financial reporting instead of the line
lists, we are adding these tiles. And
the way to
to do this is simply to navigate from
list here on this boxes here into tiles
and that would open up this kind of
report view. For each of these reports,
if data is present, you can see a
category, you can see the name, you can
see the code, you can see the status of
the report, last time you ran it and you
can see
an internal description. Now, if if no
description is is there, then it will
just be blank. If you never ran the
report, there will be no data and so on.
But hopefully this is
a different way of looking at your
financial report than just a list of
definitions.
You can also with this add, of course,
add um
views, so you can add list list views on
this. So you can kind of slice and dice
all the types of reports for different
purposes or different
processes and I'll show you more about
that both for the categories and for the
>> [clears throat]
>> and for the status.
All right, so for the authors,
we have categories, life cycle status
and these company specific defaults.
Let's look at first on report
categories.
So here on if you look at the tile, you
can see a category up here, balance
sheet.
Um and that thing there is actually a
way for you to um
just make a nicer navigation of all
reports. You can see here on the menu
for a given report, you can edit the
category both from the list, of course,
also from the report card.
And the types of categories are where we
ship, I think, 10 different types of
categories from assets and liabilities
all the way down to profitability and
revenue analysis.
If these categories don't kind of fit
what you believe is the way you would
like to categorize, you can just edit,
you can add your own
so that you make the categories
fit your finance department.
Now,
so that's mainly for navigation. Life
cycle status, here you can see one of
the reports, this one is in state
active.
But it actually allows you also as as an
author to set, here you can see the
status on the report card, active, draft
or retired. So a way for you to
communicate whether a report is ready to
use or whether you're still working on
it. And also if some of the reports are
not like used anymore, you can mark it
as retired.
These are just the states that we
introduced.
You don't have to use ours, you can you
can make your own.
And the most important thing here is
that you can define whether a report's
in a given state and this is actually
not only reports, it's all types of
definitions, so both row definitions,
column definitions and report
definitions have a state or status.
And the blocked state here is also
indicating that like if this definition
is ready to use or not. So for our
sample here, we say the active state is
the only one that is not blocked, both
draft and retired state of definitions
are considered blocked.
So how does this show? Well, first of
all, here is a draft a report that is in
state draft.
If I go here, um you can see that
there's a notification that this has
status a blocked status because the
draft status is blocked. Um and also
notice that this particular report
definition is using a row definition in
a blocked state because the act cat
row definition apparently is in in some
state, so we also show you that here
both with a different
font family, with a different color and
and with some notification.
Um and in here, the account category,
that row definition, you can also see
that this particular report row
definition has a blocked status of
retired and you can set that
state as I mentioned both on the report
definition, on the row definition and on
the column definition.
Okay. Final small thing for the, I don't
know, small, but
I actually don't think it's small. For
the report authors is ability to set
these four properties, view by, negative
number format, company logo position and
status. You can set that in one place as
a default and you do that here on the
general ledger setup on these four
types here.
What this means is that if I want minus
sign
or parentheses on all my financial
reports as the as kind of
the way I want to format my negative
numbers, I set it here.
And when I go into the actual report
definition, you can you can then see
that my negative amount format is just
default. It inherits from the global
setting on the company. If you do it
like this, then you control the negative
if all your report definition use the
default here, then you control that
property across your financial
reporting. But you can, of course,
override it on the specific report.
So that's both for the negative amount
format, for the view by.
View by is typically something where you
want to probably view by by month. So
instead of setting in every single
default report, maybe you just say the
default is
monthly and then you default on on here.
And for logos, maybe you want some
of your reports always to have your logo
in the middle part of the header and
maybe some of them shouldn't have any
logo, whatever.
Then
same thing apply, you can set the logo
position
with default.
All right,
that's it for the, author. Then for the
report consumers, we have these two new
features, dimension perspectives and
scheduling.
Dimension perspectives
um
is something where you can see here on
this particular
report or actually on the
not necessarily report, but you can set
perspectives, define dimension
perspective once and then you can use
them across things. What is this
dimension perspective? Let's take a
look.
Um
So
in on a financial report, it has always
been possible to kind of set filters on
the dimension and then run the report.
But what if you want to to run a
financial report across all
values of a dimension? For instance,
maybe you want to have a report for each
department in the department dimension.
In this old world, like until now, you
would need to run the report for each of
them, right? And then like go in here,
set the filter, run the report, set the
filter, run the report. Maybe there's a
better way. This is what dimension
perspectives is meant to do.
For this
example here, I have already defined a
perspective called department. I'm
setting that here on the report. When I
then run the report here, I'm just
starting with the print option.
You can also, as you see here, uh
perspective is shown on the request
page, so you can always override the
default that is set on on the report
when when you run it. Um
But then when you run this,
uh you get a PDF and if you look at the
page numbers of the PDF here, you have
15 pages, but over here when you look at
the page, it's
page one of three. So how come there's
15 pages in the report PDF when there's
three pages in the report? Well, that's
because here we have our balance sheets
for Kronos,
but then if we zoom out and look at the
first six pages or nine pages, you can
see that
kind of look page one, two, three and
then it's the same structure, one, two,
three, one, two, three. So let's zoom
into second row here.
And here the heading changed from
if we look at the the first heading it
was the balance sheet but now it's
changing to administration because
administration is the first value in the
department dimension. Basically we get
the report run by each value of the
this dimension and then
merged together in one PDF.
This also works for the Excel outputs.
So here
is when I run the same report and
to
to Excel. And if we just zoom in here on
the worksheets, the balance sheet is the
global num these are the no global
numbers and here we have one um
one worksheet for each value of the
dimension administration, production,
purchasing, and sales.
Uh so when I go to the next one now I
get the same financial report but
filtered to the administration
dimension.
If you open the financial report
dimension perspectives list
here I have defined three different
perspectives. I showed you how to use
the department dimension. It's it's a a
simple
perspective. You can also have more
complicated what we call custom
perspectives. If I go to
one here I call some department
here it's a custom perspective and I'm
only including two of the five values of
that dimension. So I'm picking only a
few of the cost of the department values
and then that's my perspective.
But you can even
do things across different dimensions.
So here
you see department code, customer group
code, all the different dimensions
on the x-axis. And then you simply
define a header and the combination of
values. In this case I'm doing
perspective in where I I cross
join the two
admin and sales by customer group large,
medium, small. So in this in this
example I would have six different like
invocations of the report filtered to
these combinations of dimension values
across different dimensions. So that's
perspectives dimension perspectives.
The second thing for report users is
that you can now schedule reports. So if
I go for a given report here and open
the schedules for that report
um I can now
um
define a number of schedules for that
report. In this example I've chosen to
create a weekly schedule
with a weekly
balance that's just a my description of
the schedule. I've chosen to export to
Excel and PDF. I want both this when I
run the report both these artifacts to
go to my report inbox in Business
Central but also get them by email. Um I
can set the recurrence formula here
weekly. I can even set
recipients so I can I can send this to
me, Eddie uh Mike and Lucas. In this
case here I've just said my team or this
group of people should get this schedule
of the reports.
With custom filters you can control
uh the the request page values for this
particular invocation. So in case you
have special way like you I want a a
weekly schedule of some setup of this
and sent to these people and different
schedule of these values for different
schedule you can do that.
Uh and then finally you can from here
see the the schedule logs so you can see
whatever was
run here. So the weekly schedule was run
uh here on which report and even up here
you can you can navigate to your report
inbox or to the sent emails and get
further information of the actual
artifacts that were sent.
All right. That concludes
what was done for the author then now
finally for the administrator and I'm
happy that you're still here. It I know
it's a long video. Um but I'll be quick.
The audit log is let's go back to the
tile here.
Um and you can get the audit log either
in context of a report so the audit log
for this report or all audit logs across
all reports and uh let's just go in and
see that here is the audit log for all
reports and um
and here you can then see kind of who
ran what when
um which format uh which reports
and and when it was run. We also created
filters on this page so you can you can
um easily dive into all logs last 30
days and year to date and of course you
can create your own filters.
And you can take this into analysis mode
and and do mini reports on the audit log
who ran what when um again and then you
can find
kind of get that reporting on your usage
of financial reporting and the same
goes this all of these artifacts will be
inherited if you just look at the audit
log in a filter to a to one specific
report.
That's it. Almost there. If you want to
learn more about this and other things
related to financial analytics
aka.ms/bcfinanceanalytics
is the overview page for for this and
I'm just zooming in here on um
specifically on the documentation we
have for financial reporting where
we have a lot of articles that you might
know not know of with tips and tricks
within financial reporting feature. For
instance the troubleshooting
section here with a lot of advice. If
it's too much maybe you can use the
summarize feature in Microsoft Learn and
simply get a summary of each and maybe
it would for a starting point summarize
all these and see a summary and then see
if there's something in the summary that
would be of interest then you can dive
into the content.
Um
related to this if you're interested in
this topic you probably want to watch
this video as well. So we have
a session on enhanced finance analytics.
There's a link to that video down here
in the description. So you should
definitely go and watch that if you're
interested in financial reporting.
And in general if you're interested in
analytics not only in finance but also
in sales
and other areas these are related
sessions for this release wave from
sales down to subscription billing and
even analysis mode and Power BI Excel.
So all of those links are here as well
for you to enjoy.
That's it. Stay tuned for a little bit
longer. If you do not know these general
Business Central resources stay on the
video for three more minutes. If not
then um
we are done. Thank you so much for
watching. Thanks for being part of the
launch edition.
I'm looking forward to hearing your
feedback on all the things we did for
financial reporting.
Have a great day. Thank you.
We have compiled a number of general
resources that we believe are key both
for partners but also Business Central
customers. Most Some of these are
partner some of them are also for
customers. So the first one is
called aka.ms/bcall.
This is a partner resource for that
contains lists of every other aka link
that is needed for you to understand
anything about both the Business Central
product but also processes around it.
We call these aka links because they are
called aka.ms and then for forward slash
something. And with Business Central
links we all always prefix with BC and
then something.
The next one is our partner network
social media for for Business Central
partners Viva Viva Engage. So
aka.ms/bcvivaengage
is where you go and interact with other
partners. It's not open for customers.
So this is where you can ask questions,
interact with the product group,
interact with
with with each other
in a in a closed network.
Second link a third link is for both
partners and customers. We are called
office hours. So office hours is
something we do once or twice a month
from the product group engaging with the
community about new features or things
we want to discuss. aka.ms/bcofficehours
is the is the place where you go to find
out about upcoming events. These are
recorded. I believe the recordings are
available only to partners but the live
events are available to customers as
well.
Fourth link is YouTube our YouTube
channel. I'll talk about that
in the next slide and LinkedIn in the
next slide
and then finally for for Microsoft
partners the BC's aka.ms/bcpartnerportal
is where you get
a lot of the resources as a partner such
as compete decks,
pitch decks, and a lot of other
resources.
For LinkedIn, this is our product
group's LinkedIn profile. We have 30K or
more followers, so both partners and
customers. This is the place where we
from the product group put in news and
small bits of information outside the
official channel. So, follow us
on LinkedIn to learn what's happening
right now
in in this
around the product.
And then
also on our YouTube channel, where this
is where you're probably watching this
aka.ms/bc
YouTube. We put in not only these launch
editions twice a year, but also
Co-pilot and AI video shorts, tips and
tricks, technical deep dives, under the
hood.
We even have this what's cooking where
we put little nuggets of of videos out
for new features that are even coming in
on the YouTube channel before they're
coming in the release notes. So, watch
and maybe bookmark us on YouTube. And
also notice all the playlists, so
the content is also organized in areas,
not only all the videos. So, if you have
an area that has special interest such
as analytics,
you can find them.
A playlist and kind of see all the
content related to that.
And that's it. That is truly it. We
won't
There will be no more. So, thank you for
watching all the way to the end.
And again, have a great day. Thank you.